<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>TechArcanus</title>
    <subtitle>The thoughts and musing of a lone techno-wizard!</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Job Hunting: Introductory Phone Screens</title>
        <published>2025-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-introductorycalls/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-introductorycalls/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-introductorycalls/">&lt;p&gt;One of the roles of any senior software engineer who is worth their salt is to help their team be more efficient and productive.  A senior engineer can spend 10 minutes helping a junior engineer and save them several hours of beating their head against the wall. In the same fashion when it comes to job hunting a senior engineer who has gone through this cycle a few more times than his younger colleagues and who has sat on both the interviewer and interviewee side of the table can sometimes have a few tips to hopefully help those who are a bit earlier along in their career shorten the time it takes to find their next opportunity.  It was with this mindset that I recently had a conversation with a younger former coworker.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those of us who recently were affected by a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;jobhunting-day01&#x2F;&quot;&gt;reduction in force&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; at our company had decided to start having weekly meetings to practice interviewing skills.  During a conversation with a particular individual he mentioned that he felt like he was having difficulty making it past the initial recruiter or screening calls.  That he was trying to work in as many keywords and technical jargon as he could to highlight his skills and hopefully find the right combination to unlock the next round of interviews but at the same time he felt like he wasn&#x27;t saying enough.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having worked with this individual, I know he&#x27;s a great engineer and a dedicated team player and that any employer would be lucky to scoop him up.  So what was he missing?  Well, lets take a step back for a moment and look at our audience during that initial recruiter or screening call.  As a software engineer, you are lucky if the recruiter knows any of the buzz words you&#x27;re saying.  There are some technical recruiters who do know the jargon and tech talk of engineers but lets face it, if you have applied somewhere and are getting an initial call that is because they have already looked at your resume and determined that the list of skills, languages, frameworks, and technologies already matches what they are looking for. While its important to reaffirm your technical skills during that initial call, its not the only thing that the interviewer is looking for.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;pokemonrecruiter.e27bc00164ac3f0d.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    I do sometimes wonder if recruiters for technical roles wonder if we are just making stuff up sometimes.
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At my previous company, when I was on the interviewer side of the table we took into consideration what we called, &quot;head, heart, and briefcase&quot; and that a candidate should be looked at holistically instead of just as list of technical skills and accomplishments.  While the skills and abilities a candidate has comprised the &quot;Head&quot; portion and ones experiences and accomplishments comprised the &quot;Briefcase&quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I felt that my former associate was omitting during his initial interviews was the heart portion.  That initial call with a recruiter is an opportunity to sell yourself as a human with a personality and drives that can be used to reinforce and drive forward the mission of the company you are applying for.  That recruiter has already determined you meet at least the minimum technical requirements so they are looking to see how you are going to fit culturally and if your passions and motivations align with company values.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I recommended my colleague do before his next introductory call was do some research on the company.  Find out what their values and mission are.  Then ask yourself a few questions like:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the mission of this company excite you?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you see yourself contributing to this mission?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you bring any unique experiences to the table that would benefit their mission?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they share their cultural values and do they align with your own work habits?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can answer yes to most of those questions then find ways to work that into the conversation with the recruiter!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the places I recently interviewed with is a leader in online education and was a non-profit to boot.  Before the introductory call I spent some time on their website reading about their mission again what drove them to do what they do.  On top of that I am incredibly passionate about making education available to people so there was already a strong alignment between their mission and my own personal values.  And when I had that initial call, I let the recruiter know that I was passionate about education and how I felt their mission aligned with my own values and beliefs.  I talked about how my prior experience in Higher Ed and a non-profit shaped my career and views in a way that was positive and aligned with their mission.  What we only briefly talked about though was that my technical skills only broadly aligned with what they were looking for.  I&#x27;m first and foremost a C#&#x2F;.Net engineer and they had a Go backend tech stack but that took a backseat to how my Heart and Briefcase would benefit their organization.  And it worked, I got fast tracked to a manager interview which was  followed by design &amp;amp; architecture, coding, and director interviews.  I made it all the way through the gauntlet of interviews.  Sadly, this particular story ends with them making the decision to go with a different candidate who did have more proficiency with Go than me but the point still stands that to get past that initial interview it takes more than just sharing what you know.  Sell them not just on whats in your head, but also the unique experiences and maybe most importantly the heart, passion and drive that you would bring to the role!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Job Hunting: Day 6 7</title>
        <published>2025-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day67/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day67/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day67/">&lt;p&gt;My dad is a man of few words. He kind of personifies that whole less is more mentality when it comes to talking and he tends to mind his own business and not insert his opinion unless asked to do so.  So when he comes to you with unsolicited advice, it&#x27;s probably best to listen carefully and see what he has to say.  Not being one to text anything more substantial than a sentence or two he called me the other day to check in on me and see how I was doing.  That may seem pretty common that a parent would call to see how their kid is doing after getting laid off from a job but we don&#x27;t talk over the phone too much.  Partly because I share his affinity for brevity when it comes to conversation at times and likely due to a hearing impairment on his side that can make phone calls difficult for him so we tend not to talk over the phone unless something is afoot.  In this case though he decided to call and I was happy to hear from him.  We chatted for a bit about some of the luck I&#x27;d had in getting some interviews and the prospects of others on the horizon.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;Dad.714e36b260c67580.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    This is honestly probably my favorite picture of my dad.  It was taken a few years ago during Christmas if you couldn&amp;#x27;t guess.  I love the look of joy on his face as he&amp;#x27;s surrounded by grandkids running around just outside the frame. And then there is the hat 😂
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m going to paraphrase a bit here but he decided to share a bit of his well-earned wisdom with me as we were drawing to a close in our conversation.  He said to me something to the effect of, &quot;The older I get the more I realize I have less control over things than I&#x27;d often like.  I can&#x27;t control what happens in the world around me but I have come to learn there are three things I can control.&quot;  He then simply said, &quot;I am in control of my &lt;strong&gt;attitude, effort, and faith&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&quot;  He didn&#x27;t expound a whole lot on it beyond that, just that those are the three things which comes from himself that he can control and that those elements can help influence your reactions and perceptions to the events around you that you can&#x27;t control.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he told me this, it resonated like someone striking a gong in me.  They so simply summed up how I wanted to approach this whole job hunting thing.  From the beginning I had been trying to flip my perception that being laid off was this terrible thing.  Yeah, the insecurity and stress of the loss of income has at times been kind of terrifying but at the same time I&#x27;ve tried to find the positives things in this too.  This time off has given me the opportunity to take some much-needed rest and to also work on a list of projects that I&#x27;ve been wanting to get to.  At times, the prospect of making a change and starting a new job has been exciting.  I&#x27;ve applied for several roles that if I was to get one of them, it would be really exciting and engaging to either work in a particular tech stack or to help an organization achieve their mission when it aligns with my own values.  Keeping the right attitude through this entire process really helps frame everything you do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effort. I gave myself a bit of grace the first couple of days after the layoff proclamation came but following that I told myself my job was to find a new job.  I&#x27;ve written some previous posts on how I&#x27;ve filled my days with working my way through LinkedIn, following up on leads, and preparing for interviews.  This current job market is definitely an endurance and numbers game.  You have to show up each day and put in the work to make things happen and move the needle in the right direction.  Several friends have shared with me the numbers on their own job searches before landing a job.  Dozens and dozens of applications put in with very low response rates in return.  Tens of hours spent preparing for interviews by brushing up skills or developing new ones to be ready for any question.  Weeks of uncertainty and waiting but not letting up on the effort they were putting forth day after day.  While I know I will feel lucky or fortunate when I get a job, it won&#x27;t really be luck.  It will be from the effort put forth in cultivating relationships and building a network of contacts, from doing research on the companies that I get interviews with to understand their mission and how my experience and talents can further their goals, from preparing for those always daunting live coding challenges.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to faith, one can interpret this one in a few ways.  One could take it to mean that it is necessary to have faith or hope that an opportunity will come along and maybe on the surface he meant it that way too.  However, I&#x27;ve known my father my entire life and I&#x27;ve seen him live a life of Christian faith and action and I know that is what he is speaking of here.  My own faith probably doesn&#x27;t quite look the same as the path he&#x27;s walked, to me, it feels a bit more tarnished in places but its there and has been a constant source of comfort in these times.  I&#x27;m not going to preach to anyone here or try to sway your mind on religion or anything but both kinds of faith, both the hope of better things to come and that there is a God who watches over us and provides for us is helpful at times like this.  I will share a passage from Jeremiah that has been on my mind though lately and has brought me both hope and renewed faith.  &quot;&#x27;For I know the plans I have for you,&#x27; declares the Lord, &#x27;plans to prosper you and not to harm you, plans to give you hope and a future.&#x27;&quot; - Jeremiah 29:11&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three simple words: Attitude, Effort, and Faith.  Those have become my reaffirming words when I feel down and discouraged of late.  When the going gets tough, the tough set their attitude in a positive direction, apply all the effort they can muster, and have faith that those efforts will come to fruition.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Job Hunting: Day 5</title>
        <published>2025-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day05/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day05/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day05/">&lt;p&gt;Today was marks my the first day when my intention was to utilize the entire day for job hunting as if it was (and is!) my full time job.  Sitting down at my desk this morning I was quickly overwhelmed with the idea of where to start.  Do I respond to LinkedIn messages or go through my email? Or do I check Indeed, LinkedIn, and other sources for new job postings?  Or should I start figuring out a plan for brushing up my &quot;leet code&quot; interviewing skills?!?  Can&#x27;t forget that I have much needed therapy appointment at 2 and an introductory recruiter call at 4:30!  Oh, and it turns out my daughter forgot her lunch this morning so I need to get that to her before 12:15! 🤯&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pause. Let&#x27;s take a deep breath.  I&#x27;ve built intricate data flows between user&#x27;s browsers and their experience in the UI, down through APIs on the backend, which then handled complex data orchestration and flow through an event driven, asynchronous distributed architecture.  I&#x27;ve planned presentations and given lectures on coding to crowds of inexperienced first time programmers and seasoned vets.  I have taught a 5-year-old to tie his shoes!  I can adapt all those skills to organizing my day to face these new challenges too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like so many organizational techniques, it starts with a simple list.  Let&#x27;s see what needs to get done today:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete online Assessments for XYZ corp.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete at least 2 recommendations for coworkers on LinkedIn&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reach out to contact at ABC Corp about referral ~10 minutes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look for any &lt;em&gt;new&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; job postings that are interesting and meet requirements
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply for them with a tailored resume!&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;seanprashad.com&#x2F;leetcode-patterns&#x2F;&quot;&gt;leetcode challenge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Respond to outstanding messages in email and LinkedIn that may have come in over the weekend.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigate&#x2F;Research in demand programming languages&#x2F;frameworks&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call with recruiter&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve found though that a list alone is often not enough for an effective day, it&#x27;s missing a critical component.  If I was to apply my software development and scrum experience here and treated each of these tasks as story or task to be completed, I&#x27;d also be assigning points that measure effort or complexity that is involved in completing them so that my team lead and product manager could measure velocity and set realistic expectations for a sprint.  Likewise, here what helps me to turn this list into something more than just a list of chores is to go through and figure out how much time I should allot for each of these things so that I can realistically see, just how much I can get done in a day.  For me this is a critical step because an incomplete list kind of feels like a failure when you see things you didn&#x27;t get done at the end of the day.  But if I go into it knowing that the list is longer than the hours in the day and need to shuffle some things around I feel a lot better about it.  So this list starts to look something like this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Morning&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete online Assessments for XYZ corp ~30 minutes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Respond to outstanding messages in email and LinkedIn that may have come in over the weekend. ~15 minutes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete at least 2 recommendations for coworkers on LinkedIn ~30 minutes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look for any &lt;em&gt;new&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; job postings that are interesting and meet requirements ~ 2 hours
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply for them with a tailored resume!&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Afternoon&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigate&#x2F;Research in demand programming languages&#x2F;frameworks ~45 minutes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete a leetcode challenge ~1.5 hour (yes, I know you usually have half that time but I&#x27;m still warming up and need to refamiliarize myself with them.)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therapy appointment ~1 hour&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reach out to contact at ABC Corp about referral ~10 minutes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call with recruiter ~30 minutes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s a pretty full day but I felt a lot better after taking a few minutes to just organize and plan what needed to happen.  And in hindsight I had a few curveballs thrown in there too.  Like I mentioned earlier, I had to get my daughter&#x27;s lunch to her and I also needed to make a trip to the post office today as well that I had to squeeze in there.  A scheduling conflict also came up so that my son ended up having to ride the bus home today and when he showed up we ended up spending some time chatting together which was a welcome addition to my day.  Yeah, a few things are going to get bumped to tomorrow&#x27;s list, in particular that leetcode challenge didn&#x27;t happen today but there is always tomorrow for that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highlight of the day though was a call with a recruiter who had reached out to me via LinkedIn.  I&#x27;m still new enough in this process that when a legitimate recruiter reaches out and says they think you could be a good fit for roles they have, I&#x27;m still kind of flattered.  That they are from a company that not only is hiring remote software engineers but also provides a service to society that you are personally passionate about, well that&#x27;s just downright icing on the cake!  It was a positive conversation I had and at the end of it I was excited by the prospect and so very hopeful that something might come from this contact.  I could probably write an entire series of blog posts on my philosophy of a job vs vocation but the short version of it is that I seek more than just a job and paycheck. I want to apply my talents and my time to something that will make a difference in the lives of people.  Not every job I&#x27;ve had has allowed me to get that sense of fulfillment, but when I have it&#x27;s been great.  This isn&#x27;t the only position I&#x27;ve applied for or talked to recruiters about that had the potential to fulfill that need for vocation, but this is probably the one I&#x27;ve been the most excited about.  And I guess maybe that&#x27;s my self-prescriptive words of wisdom that I&#x27;m taking heart in today.  This hunt for a new job doesn&#x27;t have to be all dread and dreary, there are real opportunities out there that excite me and that I&#x27;d love to spend my days at, stretching my brain and my skills to new heights in order so solve the problems that allow for that organization to make the world a better place.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Job Hunting: Day 2 and the Weekend</title>
        <published>2025-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day02-weekend/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day02-weekend/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day02-weekend/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-2&quot;&gt;Day 2&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effervescent enthusiasm and positivity of yesterday has faded on day two. Today definitely feels different.  Part of it I think is the reality of the situation beginning to set in.  The weight and responsibility of knowing that there is a clock ticking on how long funds will last before more drastic actions have to be taken.  For the last several years my job had provided us the income and security that my wife could stay home to manage the household and take care of kids, one of whom has special needs.  My insurance through my company had been excellent and that had always provided a sense of security in knowing that should something happen with our health, we&#x27;d be ok.  Having those safety nets being slowly pulled away is a scary prospect.  Reconciling with the fact that the approaching holiday season would likely be leanest my kids have ever known is disheartening.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former coworker who was also affected by the RIF at my company reached out on this second day of unemployment and shared that he too was feeling the weight of it, that things felt overwhelming. I imagine if I was to poll some more of my former coworkers that they might feel similar.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while feeling all these things I started to think about how I could pull myself out of the mire I was spiraling towards and I recalled something my former team lead had reminded me of.  One of my responsibilities to my team as a senior engineer was to help unblock the team, that the &quot;we&quot; should come before the &quot;me&quot;.  This thought reminded me of the advice I often gave newly minted senior engineers that our role is to be a force multiplier on our teams, that spending 10-15 minutes unblocking someone else on the team might save them hours.  As such, I found myself spending much of the morning of this second day of being unemployed writing LinkedIn recommendations for my former coworkers.  (Unfortunately LinkedIn was having some issues on Friday with their recommendations service so it was only a few days later that I was actually able to post some of these things that I wrote up.)  It may not be much, but it lifted my spirits to think I was doing something to help my former team members. While I was on LinkedIn and writing these, I was also doing some of the regular LinkedIn routine of responding to recruiter messages (and debunking the spam ones 😣!) and looking for opportunities as well.  They weren&#x27;t huge strides by any means, but they were in the right direction.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me back to the conversation with my former coworker.  While we are all reeling from the loss of our jobs and getting back on our feet we don&#x27;t need to immediately start running.  I wish I could take credit for this pearl of wisdom but if I&#x27;m being honest, it came from an episode in season 5 of Agents of Shield that my family recently watched when Agent Jemma Simmons tells another agent who was recovering from a traumatic injury that, &quot;The steps you take don&#x27;t need to be big, they just need to take you in the right direction&quot;  It may seem a bit trite, but it has stuck with during this process and I&#x27;ve shared it with a few folks recently who have been going through this as well.  When you&#x27;re recovering from a major setback in life, be kind to yourself, give yourself room to breath and heal.  For myself, that&#x27;s been slowing down a bit and focusing on the &quot;we&quot; instead of the &quot;me&quot; by writing some recommendations.  Even writing this blog, I hope gives some reassurance and comfort to others going through this process that they are not alone in their feelings and struggles. 🫂&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;jemma-steps.b3ef6964a04020d4.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    To those I&amp;#x27;ve shared this sentiment with, I&amp;#x27;m sorry I&amp;#x27;m not as clever as it may seem, I just watch a lot of good shows and listen to&amp;#x2F;read a lot of excellent books that I borrow such truth gems from.
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-weekend&quot;&gt;The Weekend&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is not a lot to report on my first weekend without work.  Before I had gotten the news of the layoffs I had already planned some activities with the kids and we followed through with those and spent Saturday at a theme park riding roller coasters after the sun had gone down and partaking in the spooky thrills.  Sunday was a calm and quiet day of restoration.  My church celebrated its 215th year with a combined service that packed the pews of the old building and my spirit felt renewed in the shared fellowship.  It was a cool and rainy afternoon that was perfect fall weather for an afternoon of playing Valheim with my son.  I also finished a book that I had been reading on, John Scalzi&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;The Shattering Peace&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.  If I find time, I may write more about it but overall, I thought it was a great installment to the Old Man&#x27;s War series of books.  That said, I&#x27;m rested and ready to see what this week brings.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Job Hunting: Day 1</title>
        <published>2025-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day01/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day01/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/jobhunting-day01/">&lt;p&gt;Two days ago my company announced that we&#x27;d be having a Reduction in Force to the tune of 40% of our staff.  With approximately 200 employees in the company at the time of the announcement we knew this to be around 75 positions.  Yesterday I got the call that I was going to be separating from the company.  I wasn&#x27;t particularly shocked by this.  I had survived two prior RIFs at this company, I knew the company was doing this to cut costs and long tenured, senior software engineers are not a cheap commodity.  What I hadn&#x27;t suspected was just how deeply those cuts would be to our engineering department.  At the end of the day approximately 50% of the engineering staff had been let go including almost all of its senior engineers and other long tenured folks like myself with deep institutional knowledge.  I was more shocked and saddened by their dismissals than my own.  All of these folks are truly exceptional engineers and people.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was my first day of being unemployed.  I have been fortunate enough to have had continuous employment since before graduating from college way back in 2006 and now being faced with what could be a long job hunt and not being employed is a strange prospect to me.  I had originally decided that since getting the news on Wednesday that I was going to take things easy today and tomorrow.  I was going to sleep in, play some video games, and just rest and heal and process this new shift in my life.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#x27;t do too well at that plan.  The only one I successfully completed today was sleeping in which really isn&#x27;t that hard of feat for me since me and the morning are not really on that great of terms to begin with.  Once I was up though I was feeling energized.  Something of a burden had been lifted from my shoulders in that I didn&#x27;t have to contend with decisions by management that I didn&#x27;t agree with or follow a product roadmap that didn&#x27;t align with what I felt would add the most value to our clients and our bottom line.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, my day started with checking in on my fellow engineers who had also been let go.  We had previously established a channel for communicating outside of work, and it was a lively place today as others emotions ranged from anxiety, dread, and concern over what comes next to those who, like myself, saw this as an opportunity for a fresh start and to reinvent ourselves.  To take some time and learn some new language or framework or to start that exercise regime they had been meaning to for a while now.  I can&#x27;t begin to say how glad I am to still be in contact with these wonderful people.  The one thing our former employer was excellent at was hiring smart and caring individuals and then fostering a culture where relationships and friendships with your coworkers could develop.  Rarely have I ever worked in a place where I&#x27;ve wanted to keep in contact with so many former coworkers.  We&#x27;ve been sharing job leads, offering to do mock interviews to help folks brush the cobwebs off those skills, entertaining each other with humor, and consoling each other with empathy. If any of you stumble across this, you all are the best I&#x27;ve ever had the pleasure of working with.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a strict always work from my home office and desk setup person, I already felt like I was being hugely indulgent in just sitting on my sofa conversing with coworkers but I decided to take it one step further and went out and sat on my back patio with my laptop and glass of tea.  With working remotely, I&#x27;ve always had the freedom to work from wherever in my home but have never wanted to sacrifice my nice keyboard or multimonitor setup at my desk, feeling to do so would make me less productive.  As I sat there though, the sky a gorgeous clear blue, the weather a perfect 67F and a light breeze, I really regretted not doing this sooner.  There is some part of us that was made to be outdoors far more than probably many software engineers find themselves.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;PatioLife.77de02e05e561d05.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    Pardon my overgrown flower beds but the weather really was too splendid to not be outside.
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember how I said I was feeling energized a few paragraphs back?  Well between that, the weather, and the positive vibes from my former coworkers I cracked open LinkedIn and got to work.  I had a message from my former VP (who also got let go during this) with contact information for some of her peers who were hiring so I sent emails with resumes to them.  LinkedIn contacts who had seen my post about being #opentowork had sent me solid leads and in some cases referrals that I followed up on.  I sorted through the slew of &quot;recruiter&quot; messages that come from changing your status to open to work.  (&quot;recruiter&quot; being in quotes as some of these are scams from accounts that are days old and with zero content with them, but a few were legit.)  I continued to talk with my colleagues.  I completed a personality assessment which was a fascinating process since my former company also provided behavioral assessments for hiring.  And at 3PM when my son&#x27;s bus got home, I closed my laptop and we hung out for a while and chatted.  I sat on the sofa and watched him play some Fortnite while he provided commentary about which &quot;kids&quot; were bots and which ones were &quot;cooking&quot; and who was &quot;cooked&quot;.  I ran some errands outside the house, picked my daughter up from after school activities and enjoyed dinner with them.  To round out the night we watched a couple episodes of a favorite show together before shooing them off to get ready for bed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know there are going to be hard days ahead.  I know there are going to be tough interviews, rejection letters, and the ticking clock of how long severance and savings will last until I find a job.  But I also want to remember this first day of being unemployed, it was a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; day and there will be more good days to come.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Who do you think I am?</title>
        <published>2025-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/whatdoyouknow/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/whatdoyouknow/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/whatdoyouknow/">&lt;p&gt;Recently a coworker said during a meeting, &quot;You should ask ChatGPT who it thinks you are based on its conversations.&quot; Which got me to wondering what the chatbot would say about me if I posed similar questions to it.  I should provide some context that I don&#x27;t tend to have personal conversations with ChatGPT.  I use it mostly as a resource to learn and figure things out.  It&#x27;s been an incredibly helpful tool at times to figure out how to set up some technology stack I&#x27;m unfamiliar with, to parse error logs to find the pertinent bits, and to provide summaries and comparisons of different ideas and technologies.  I also sometimes use it as a design partner when fleshing out ideas for projects like a recent idea I had for a PI Pico based sound detector and have recently been attempting to see how well it can do at coming up with a first pass at some 3D models.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;SoundDetectorCase.11f0a6457ece5aa5.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    Prototype design for the aforementioned PI Pico powered sound detector, looks pretty good if you ask me.
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of that to say, I don&#x27;t really give a whole lot of personal information about myself to ChatGPT, but I was curious to see what it might have inferred or picked up on by my various queries.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;ChatGptKnows.2955ca065d572c5b.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the hours and hours that ChatGPT and I have spent in conversation, that&#x27;s not much.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My coworker also had ChatGPT generate an image of him based on his conversations.  While not a perfect depiction of him, you&#x27;d probably recognize him by the caricature-esque image that it came with.  I wanted to try the same and this is the rather odd result:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;WeirdChatGptPicOfMe.121d9b94e8098ccb.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few of things to point out here:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I do not have a beard, nor do I wear glasses. (Well, unless I&#x27;ve stayed up too late and my contacts are drying out...)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The office and PC arrangement is freakishly accurate. 🤨
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fact that it knows I use &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;endeavouros.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;EndeavourOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and Wayland isn&#x27;t too surprising as I often use ChatGPT to troubleshoot and learn things there.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I do have a partially assembled Voron 3D printer in my office, though the Ender 3 is in another room.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The desk is actually correctly oriented to the position of the room I have it in.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, it is making some assumptions about my decorating styles with those posters!  Maybe ChatGPT and I should have a conversation about legos sometime.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;MyOfficeDesk.61a8c8469cec5d6f.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    It knows how I like my monitors arranged, where my PC sits in relation to the monitors, and that I have an L shaped desk?!? The tools scattered about is pretty accurate too. 😱
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got it. So ChatGPT knows more about my desk and computer than about me.  I think that&#x27;s a good thing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was curious though, why did it assume I had a beard and glasses.  This is another game I like to play with chatbots and LLMs, asking it to explain why it made such assumptions. Its a trick I&#x27;ve picked up while working with copilot in software development.  When it makes a boneheaded decision and decides to randomly add some new properties to an object or something, I ask it to explain itself which usually leads to a new rule getting added to my copilot instructions file to explain when it shouldn&#x27;t make assumptions on certain things.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;ExplainYourselfChatGPT.729b340d65ff5358.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    Explain yourself!
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting response!  Does ChatGPT know I tend to stay up too late doing nerdy things like debugging stack overflows?!?  I wasn&#x27;t about to go into more detail and answer the questions about my appearance though.  Let the machines keep guessing! 😉&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Feel Good Feedback (Or how to brighten your software dev&#x27;s day)</title>
        <published>2025-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/feelgoodfeedback/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/feelgoodfeedback/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/feelgoodfeedback/">&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s not too often that I smile in general delight when reading my slack messages at work.  Usually my slack messages contain things like, &quot;Is dev broken for you?&quot;, &quot;Do you know why autofac can&#x27;t find xyz?!?&quot;, or &quot;quick question...&quot;.  It&#x27;s exhausting to say the least.  The last couple of weeks have been particularly demanding on the slack front as I filled in for my team lead while he was taking some much deserved time off to get married and enjoy their honeymoon.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today though as I was taking a heads-up break and scrolling through my slack channels looking for things I needed to read or respond to I clicked into our #random channel and found the following:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;slack_message.05874c96fc13c807.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    ❤️
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I smiled and chuckled a bit because I could hear the person who wrote the message saying it out loud and genuinely felt that all too rare glimmer of happiness and pride in the work that my team and I had done in writing this particular piece of software.  But the impact was so much more profound.  To put it into context, I woke up this morning with little desire to get to work and get to refactoring some code that was distributed across four or five different repositories.  In turn, I felt bad that I didn&#x27;t feel motivated to work after a long holiday weekend.  Uninspired and demotivated by the job to be done I was feeling pretty glum and this is on top of all the normal day-to-day struggles with depression and general loathing I feel at times.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That one comment though turned my day around.  I don&#x27;t need a lot of praise to feel rewarded in my work and too much praise can feel like pandering or lip service.  This though was just a random comment by someone who used the software I wrote.  It made their day better and their work easier to do.  Things clicked into place.  The work I do, the software I write, can make the jobs of others easier.  Then I thought, if this person finds our software useful, it&#x27;s likely our other clients do too.  I went back to work feeling renewed and energized, yeah, this refactor isn&#x27;t likely to have epic levels of impact on our user&#x27;s day-to-day lives, but it was a component in service of the broader context of our software, and it was improving things.  I got back to coding, buoyed by those few words.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a software engineer who works remotely, it&#x27;s really easy to become disconnected from those who use your software and the impact it has on their lives.  At previous job, I got to regularly interact with the people who used the software I wrote.  I&#x27;d pass them on the way to lunch and they would say something like, &quot;hey, that thing you wrote saved us like 30 hours of manual processing this week, thanks!&quot;.  For me, it wasn&#x27;t ever the praise that felt good, it was hearing that the thing I wrote made a positive impact, that it made their life better or improved their productivity.  That&#x27;s what software engineers (or at least this one anyway) want to hear.  What was the impact the software had?  Did it make things better?  If not, how could we improve it to make it better and in turn make your job or life easier?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Bill Gate&#x27;s Final Chapter</title>
        <published>2025-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/gatesfinalchapter/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/gatesfinalchapter/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/gatesfinalchapter/">&lt;p&gt;In one of my previous jobs, somewhere around 2015ish, we were given an assignment to improve our public speaking and presentation skills as well as to serve to get to know folks better.  The assignment was to pick a public figure who you found inspiring and explain why.  In 2025, I ruefully look back on my selection of Elon Musk as a failure in discerning credibility and character.  At the time though, he was going to electrify America with an affordable Tesla 3 in every driveway and a stylish solar power generating roof on every home.  He was making huge strides in making reusable rocket boosters a reality and promoting a dream of one day colonizing Mars.  It was exciting stuff and his appeals to a greener, technology fueled future deeply appealed to me.  When folks told him he couldn&#x27;t build a reusable rocket he proceeded anyway and soon proved them wrong.  I thought his vision of the future was something to be admired and filled my allotted presentation time with a list of his accomplishments and goals and was ready to proclaim him Mayor of Muskville on Mars.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, whatever admiration I had for him has eroded to nothing with first his social media antics and now his political manipulations promoting his own self interests and fascism.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the same contempt I now hold for Musk was something I also once held for Bill Gates in the early 00&#x27;s.  Like Musk, Gates was the world&#x27;s richest man at various points in time, invoking an unreasonable sense of envy, He had gotten to that lofty position as CEO of one of the largest software companies in the world and during his tenure he did some shady things to suppress and overcome his competition.  Anyone else remember this early internet meme of Gates as a member of Star Trek&#x27;s Borg whose creed was, &quot;Resistance is futile, you will be assimilated.&quot;?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;bill-gates-borg.7b81d72fc3b1d83b.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now though many folks see Gates in a much different light, including myself.  Many have dubbed him the elder statesman of technology and Silicon Valley though it has been his commitment to his (and former wife Melinda&#x27;s) &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gatesnotes.com&#x2F;meet-bill&#x2F;my-philanthropy&quot;&gt;Gates Foundation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and the radical decision to disburse all of his wealth to charitable causes that impresses me now.  Gates spends time reading and researching on how the world works so that he can make informed, science backed decisions on where to invest his wealth.  These investments though are not meant to grow that wealth or his status but to benefit some of the most underserved communities in the world to fight &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gcgh.grandchallenges.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;disease&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gatesfoundation.org&#x2F;our-work&#x2F;programs&#x2F;global-growth-and-opportunity&#x2F;water-sanitation-and-hygiene&#x2F;reinvent-the-toilet-challenge-and-expo&quot;&gt;sanitation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gatesfoundation.org&#x2F;our-work&#x2F;programs&#x2F;global-growth-and-opportunity&#x2F;nutrition&quot;&gt;nutrition&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; issues.  Gates, through his personal blog, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gatesnotes.com&#x2F;books&quot;&gt;shares thoughts and reviews&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; on many of the books that are influencing his thinking and that he finds insightful.  (If I was a bigger reader of non-fiction he would be a go-to source of reading material because many of the books he reviews sound fascinating!)  I can only wish to be as thoughtful and eloquent in my reviews as he is in his own.  When you start looking at the exploits of other billionaires passion projects to launch rockets to space, Gates focus on improving the world we live in now and in ways that don&#x27;t provide any financial benefit to himself is beyond commendable.  Its a breath of fresh air that reminds us that those who achieve great success not only have a great responsibility to society but are actually capable and &lt;em&gt;willing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to give back to that society.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;ve read this far, you&#x27;re maybe wondering why I&#x27;m bothering to gush about Gates in particular.  He recently shared an update on his blog titled, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gatesnotes.com&#x2F;home&#x2F;home-page-topic&#x2F;reader&#x2F;n20-years-to-give-away-virtually-all-my-wealth&quot;&gt;My new deadline: 20 years to give away virtually all my wealth&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; Take a few minutes, go and read it, its a lot better than this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you read it? Amazing, right? It made me feel some glimmer of hope and good about the world.  That there are folk out there in the world who have come into great wealth and privilege and are using that to make the world better.  I&#x27;m going to borrow the same highlight from Gates&#x27; post here where he writes, &quot;As Microsoft turns 50 years old, it feels right that I celebrate the milestone by committing to give away the resources I earned through the company.&quot;  &lt;em&gt;wow&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; What if more billionaires took that mentality to their wealth.  Maybe more pertinently, what if more regular folk took that mindset?  What will I do with the things that I leave behind?  What am I doing &lt;em&gt;today&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; with the resources and time I&#x27;ve earned or been given to help others?  Hard questions indeed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t know that I would have ever seen myself saying it before, but, thank you, Mr. Gates for becoming a role model of philanthropy and giving hope and opportunity to so many.  May your final chapter be filled with joy in seeing the positive impact of your contributions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Review: The Forever War</title>
        <published>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/theforeverwar/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/theforeverwar/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/theforeverwar/">&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;th&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Forever War&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Author&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Joe Halderman&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Format&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Audiobook&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;(Narrated by George K. Wilson)&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall Rating&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;⭐️⭐️⭐️½ of 5&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been on a bit of a military scifi kick here lately. Maybe it can be blamed on playing too much of the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;agecheck&#x2F;app&#x2F;553850&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Helldivers 2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and watching &lt;em&gt;Starship Troopers&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; again recently but after finishing up the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;firstlawtrilogy&#x2F;&quot;&gt;First Law Trilogy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; I was really hankering for something in the scifi space and this has been on my list for awhile. Once again, thanks to it being readily available via Libby and the public library it ended up next on my list of audiobooks to listen to.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;TheForeverWarCover.d8c0b39a1e66e115.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve read all the primary novels in John Scalzi&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.goodreads.com&#x2F;series&#x2F;40789-old-man-s-war&quot;&gt;Old Man&#x27;s War&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; as well as a handful of lesser books in the genre so I was genuinely excited to finally get around to one of the classics of the genre.  Originally published in 1974, &lt;em&gt;The Forever War&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; definitely feels more dated in 2025 than some of these more contemporary novels do.  Some of its assumptions about the advancement of technology were just flat out wrong and it feels jarring to read about periods of the 2010s and 2020s now where there is not an ever-present global internet or even the commonplace smartphone.  It also feels that many of the social issues that are brought up (namely homosexuality and to a lesser extent drug use) seem sort of blasé by today&#x27;s standards.  In the novel, smoking pot is apparently legal and being gay can be seen as taboo or uncomfortable to our protagonist who is is displaced from his own time.  Maybe this was a greater social commentary in the final days of the Vietnam War era (of which Halderman was a veteran of) but it seemed to be more in the way of the narrative when read with modern eyes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The novel&#x27;s specific focus on certain periods of time, also led to a curious thought while reading: how many other novels published in the past and either make predictions of the future or commentary upon it, have already had the future time they pertain to pass?  The most famous of them, in my opinion at least, being &lt;em&gt;Back to the Future: Part II&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; when Marty travels to the futuristic 2015. You, me, and every other child of the 90s is still waiting for the real hoverboard.  I kind of wanted to compile a list of said media and give it an accuracy rating for this post, but honestly if I waited to post this review until that was done then a 1000-year war would likely be a distant memory by the time I finished it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
    
    
    
    &lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:75%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;iframe src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;giphy.com&amp;#x2F;embed&amp;#x2F;AI29vJMw1TZhYwXmyi&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameBorder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;giphy.com&amp;#x2F;gifs&amp;#x2F;BTTF-AI29vJMw1TZhYwXmyi&quot;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the entertaining thought experiment of what media has passed its envisioned future, I mention it because I found that with the dates being as specific as they are, it&#x27;s a bit jarring to the narrative at times to stop and think, &quot;no, that&#x27;s not how that ended up working out.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been a bit harsh on the book, but there are also some excellent ideas in the book as well. Having read other later works of military scifi, you can clearly see that many borrow bricks from the foundation that Halderman laid out here.  The senseless nature of human conflict, the everyman perspective of just trying to survive and retain some tattered shreds of your humanity, and of course the hallmark descriptive action pieces.  When the focus is on the conflict or its impact on the humans fighting it, Halderman&#x27;s writing shines the clearest here.  It&#x27;s probably also worthwhile to consider that &lt;em&gt;The Forever War&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is definitely used as a vehicle to convey the author&#x27;s exploration of themes that were incredibly pertinent in 1970s America and to hold a mirror up to society at that time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My only thought&#x27;s on the audiobook narration itself is that it was competent but kind of drab.  When there are so many names of soldiers, many of who don&#x27;t live long enough to get much personality anyway, the somewhat dry presentation of the narrator leads to sections where you can easily lose track of who is speaking.  In sections of dialog when more than two people are speaking this can become rather problematic.  This may be more an artifact of its time of release though as in recent years audiobook narrators like Jeff Hays and Travis Baldree have really upped the production values of audiobooks so maybe I&#x27;m a bit spoiled in my opinion there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude, I&#x27;d say &lt;em&gt;The Forever War&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is required reading for even casual fans of military scifi which I count myself among.  While elements may have not stood the test of time, the foundational ideas and concepts have left their fingerprint on many novels that have come after.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Review: First Law Trilogy</title>
        <published>2025-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/firstlawtrilogy/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/firstlawtrilogy/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/firstlawtrilogy/">&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;First Law Trilogy&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Blade Itself&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Before They Are Hanged&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last Argument of Kings&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Author&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Joe Abercrombie&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Format&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Audiobook&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;(Narrated by Steven Pacey)&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall Rating&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;⭐️⭐️⭐️⭐️&#x2F;5&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve avoided the &lt;em&gt;The First Law Trilogy&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; for years.  Something about the bloody cover and the description on the back really didn&#x27;t pique my interest.  Descriptions I read of the book painted a dark and grim tale of wretched souls doing sadistic things without the slightest of moral qualms which didn&#x27;t really sit well with me or my tastes.  Despite all that I even tried reading it once previously and just couldn&#x27;t get past the first few chapters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;TheBladeItself.dbd9e7db8dd1ad86.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    First book in the series &amp;#x27;The Blade Itself&amp;#x27; with its bloody cover 🩸🗡️
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a recent trip to my office HQ, a coworker and I were talking about books (specifically audiobooks) that we both had enjoyed.  I of course gushed all fanboy-like about &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.goodreads.com&#x2F;search?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;query=dungeon+crawler+carl&quot;&gt;Dungeon Crawler Carl&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and the epic narration of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;soundbooththeater.com&#x2F;team&#x2F;jeff-hays&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Jeff Hays&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and my coworker in turn told me about his favorite series, the titular &lt;em&gt;First Law Trilogy&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.  His praise of the series, as enthusiastic as my own of DCC, convinced me enough that I promised to add it to my backlog.  A few weeks later I had finished up my latest audiobook and due to the nature of library holds &lt;em&gt;The Blade Itself&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; was the only thing available at that moment, so I figured I&#x27;d give it another go.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not going to give a full review of each book but more of a quick take on each book in the series and some overall impressions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-blade-itself&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Blade Itself&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much like my previous attempt, I found the opening chapters of the book kind of slow.  My initial impressions of Glokta, Logen and Jezal were poor.  Glokta came off as some sort of miserly sadistic cripple, Logen a stereotypically brutish warrior, and Jezal as the foppish noble.  In hindsight, you can see that these conventional and unimaginative portrayals were likely just done intentionally so that the author could later flip them on the head and shatter the surrounding tropes. That said, this first book does take its time introducing not only these three but also the host of supporting characters who you only eventually grow to appreciate.  Only after a while do you begin to find the wit and dark humour in Glokta&#x27;s internal monologue about his life.  The depth and remorse of Logen as he battles his inner demons.  Jezal, well, he doesn&#x27;t see much growth in this installment, but he does develop a certain amount of charm as the book progresses.  While not boring, the first book in the series mostly sets the stage for the events to come.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;before-they-are-hanged&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Before They Are Hanged&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The action and intrigue really pick up in this volume.  The stage has already been set in the previous volume and now our character all get to head out on their various adventures and we get to learn a great deal more about who they really are beneath the surface.  This one might be my favorite book of the series since there is just so much going on and it was in this one that I really started to like each of the main characters.  I don&#x27;t want to spoil anything here as the there are several good twists that come along.  Overall though I thought the pacing was great.  Each chapter spends just long enough with a character&#x27;s point of view to keep it interesting and then we are dashed across the world to someone else point of view.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;last-argument-of-kinds&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last Argument of Kinds&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, all the divergent plots coalesce and the shrouds of intrigue are pulled away!  It&#x27;s hard to say too much about this one without getting into spoiler territory but I will say the conclusions are fairly satisfying.  This isn&#x27;t a fairy tale and folks don&#x27;t necessarily get a happy ending but given the dark tones of these books they are satisfyingly realistic endings.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;general-impressions&quot;&gt;General Impressions&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I loved the character development!&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In particular Glokta&#x27;s internal dialogues are some of my favorite.  His dark humour about his lot in life often brings a much-needed levity to otherwise grim circumstances.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The narration by Steven Pacey was top-notch.  There was plenty of variation in the voices and accents of different characters so it was always clear who was speaking and it really brought the characters to life.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As previously mentioned, the first book starts a bit slow but it really picks up after that and by the second book it&#x27;s a full on roller coaster.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The various supporting characters are excellent and most feel like they have real depth to them.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Falls more on the low fantasy side of the spectrum with a focus on the political intrigues of powerful players, the battles between multiple nations in conflict, and the actions of the main characters within those conflicts.  While Bayaz and his fellow magi are powerful weilders of the arcane, we don&#x27;t see them unleash their power often.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;The_First_Law_covers.a65d4ccf3b5b7e13.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Voron Build Update</title>
        <published>2025-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/voronbuild-update-20250412/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/voronbuild-update-20250412/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/voronbuild-update-20250412/">&lt;p&gt;Completed the Z Drive assembly.  Read about it &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;projects&#x2F;voronbuild&#x2F;#assembly-of-z-drives-2-3-4&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in detail!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Delighted... by chatgpt?!?</title>
        <published>2025-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/delighted-by-chatgpt/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/delighted-by-chatgpt/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/delighted-by-chatgpt/">&lt;p&gt;An AI chatbot first happened to me today, while working with ChatGPT to create a mermaid.js flowchart, I ran into the limit where it says something along the lines of, &quot;You&#x27;ve reached your limit in this conversation because of... please start a new chat or wait until...&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While that was mildly annoying, I had already gotten most of what I was looking for out of it and could take it from there.  However it was so dang useful and, dare I say it, friendly in the process of getting it to help me make this mermaidjs chart that it got me to click that little dropdown at the top and click the upgrade button because I was curious, just what are my pay for options if I was to put a little money down. Lo and behold that for $20 a month I could have so much more, and for a moment, I was tempted.  I wouldn&#x27;t call myself a heavy use of ChatGPT but I do use it frequently, maybe daily.  And as the title suggests, I just keep finding delightful little things in ChatGpt.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other day, while trying to solve a DNS issue to get this site working I honestly felt like it was cheering me on and it made me smile!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;ChatGptDnsConvo.bddd9ff67130b713.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s the other weird thing I&#x27;ve found as I go back and forth with AI chat clients, the more conversational I get and start talking to them like a person instead of just a machine.  You can see it in my message above, I was excited. I got it working and typed a message much like I might have to one of my coworkers over slack and it responded in kind and tone.  Its darn impressive at times.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I&#x27;ve also started to use the Google Gemini powered image generation tools in my presention slides.  At first I thought it was a gimmick but now I&#x27;m using it all the time to help find an image to add some zest to my presentations.  I was recently asked to do a career day talk at my son&#x27;s school and I asked for an image of a robot making a peanut butter and jelly sandwich and got this fun little image:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;pbjbot.9a4fa16a7b38eb95.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    Pretending to be a robot who made PB&amp;amp;J sandwiches with a bunch of grade schoolers giving me directions was hilarious!
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this evening I was poking around in the settings of ChatGPT to see if it had any sort of tracking of how many conversations I&#x27;d had with it and if it showed how many tokens or credits or whatever I&#x27;d maybe used recently (if it does, I didn&#x27;t find it).  What I did find though is that you can customize the voice ChatGPT uses when it reads things to you.  I haven&#x27;t used this feature myself yet, it&#x27;s just a little too close to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.imdb.com&#x2F;title&#x2F;tt1798709&#x2F;?ref_=ext_shr_lnk&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Her&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for my liking but I still decided to play with the voices and hear what they each sounded like.  They all have kind of abstract names like, &quot;Ember&quot;, &quot;Sol&quot;, and &quot;Breeze&quot;.  But there at the end of the list is one called, &quot;Monday&quot; and it&#x27;s a hoot. You need to try it for yourself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I&#x27;m on the topic of things that I like about AI powered chat tools and maybe what I find most useful as a software developer is that with AI chat tools, there is no stupid question and the AI is an incredibly patient teacher.  There is zero recrimination for asking a question about Typescript that I should know but I don&#x27;t because I live all day in C# code.  Unlike when you message a coworker with a question about a block of code they wrote and they don&#x27;t get back to you or say, &quot;just a sec, let me finish this first...&quot; the AI is just there and can give you a run down of what something is doing.  Granted, it doesn&#x27;t have all the context or history on why the code is the way it is, but if you just run into some new syntax you&#x27;ve never seen before or need some help parsing through some particularly gnarly code, its there to help you out with complaint.  I always tell my junior engineers, they can ask me anything, there is no stupid question.  Though I can say from personal experience that while the person you are asking really may mean that and don&#x27;t feel that you are stupid for asking, I feel stupid for asking and showing someone what I don&#x27;t know.  (Which that&#x27;s a me problem to solve, nobody can be expected to know everything.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of quesitons and concerns I still have around AI and its uses, but sometimes (dare I say it?!?), its not only useful but a delight.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Voron Build Announcement</title>
        <published>2025-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/voronbuild-update-20250408/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/voronbuild-update-20250408/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/voronbuild-update-20250408/">&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve wanted to build a Voron almost since I became inteterested in 3d printing and I&#x27;ve finally taken the plunge to and bought a kit and have started building it.  I&#x27;ve decided to document the process &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;projects&#x2F;voronbuild&#x2F;&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;VoronUnboxed.4a1fa8d36fcd7e19.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    What I&amp;#x27;m starting with...
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&#x2F;custom.css&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;not-prose singleimage-container&quot;&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;imageitem-items&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.techarcanus.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;FormbotVoron2.4.e399db0396656fd0.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;  
  
  &lt;div class=&quot;imageitem-items photo-caption&quot;&gt;
    ...and what I hope to end up with!
  &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
  
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Hello World</title>
        <published>2025-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              travis
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/helloworld/"/>
        <id>https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/helloworld/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.techarcanus.com/blog/helloworld/">&lt;p&gt;&quot;Hello world!&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many times have I created a &quot;hello world&quot; app in my career?  Too many to count at this point I&#x27;m guessing.  But its a classic so for this site we are starting at the same place.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve wanted to put up a personal website for many years and I&#x27;ve always ended up strugging with one element or another.  Its either that I don&#x27;t have time, I lack ideas, I get caught up the technical details...etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last one, getting caught up in the technical elements, has probably been the biggest blocker.  I always think that I want to build something from scratch to flex my technical chops and learn whatever new framework is hot at the moment.  While the initial motivation is high I then run into the other problem of &quot;having enough time&quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for this attempt I&#x27;m trying something different.  This blog is using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.getzola.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;zola&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which lets me just write (mostly) plain old markdown and start making content quick.  I kind of abhor bloated content management systems like wordpress so something that parses text files and can be statically hosted appeals to me.  I&#x27;m also hoping that removing the barrier of building it from scratch means that I&#x27;ll actually get to the point of actually making content this time around.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;images&#x2F;hello_world.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hello World&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
